Guide to the James A. Kelly collection of Brooklyn firefighting records 1989.006
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 6: New Lots Volunteer Fire Department, 1866-1949
  - Minutes (ledger 115), 1886-1894 (Box 20)
  - Dues accounts (ledger 116), 1886-1894 (Box 20)
  - Minute Book of the Board of Directors of New Lots Exempt Firemen's Association (ledger 81), 1886-1949 (Box 17)
  - Minutes of New Lots Firemen's Association (ledger 71), 1886-1894 (Box 16)
  - Minutes of the New Lots Exempt Firemen's Association (ledger 141), 1894-1908 (Box 22)
  - Constitution and By-Laws of the New Lots Exempt Firemen's Association (ledger 151), 1900 (Box 22)
  - New Lots Exempt Firemen's Association (ledger 156), 1900-1902 (Box 23)
  - Dues accounts (ledger 54), 1903-1913 (Box 13)
  - New Lots Firemen's Association (minutes) (ledger 45), 1923-1934 (Box 12)
  - Roll book (dues accounts) (ledger 149), undated (Box 22)
- Series 7: State and National Firefighting Associations, 1864-1952
  Sub-series 7.1: Ledgers
  Sub-series 7.2: Documents
  The series contains material generated by county, state, and national firefighting organizations and associations between 1864 and 1952. Included are rolls, dues accounts, and exemption certificates. The bulk of this series is made up of materials pertaining to the New York State Conference, Order of American Firemen (NYSCOAF), including correspondence, reports, and meeting notices.
  - Sub-series 7.1: Ledgers, 1864-1952
    - Names of Substitutes and Volunteers paid by the King's County Bounty Committee (ledger 109), 1864-1865 (Box 20)
    - Dues accounts of Exempt Firemen's Association of Queens, Fifth Ward (ledger 89), 1887-1930 (Box 18)
    - Flatlands Volunteer Firemen's Association (ledger 99), 1888-1925 (Box 19)
    - Accounts, New York State Conference, Order of American Firemen (NYSCOAF) (ledger 184), 1893-1896 (Box 24)
    - Exemption Certificates, Kings County (ledger 192), 1896 (Box 20)
    - Volunteer Firemen, King's County (roll) (ledger 41), 1896-1952 (Box 12)
    - Dues and Assessments, Engine Company No. 10, Fourth District (ledger 44), 1903-1910 (Box 12)
  - Sub-series 7.2: Documents, 1864-1942
    - Ephemera: tickets, receipts, invitations, cards, petitions for monuments from: Queens, King's County Volunteer Association, Firemen's Association of New York, 1864-1931 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - New York City Fire Department membership resolution regarding the death of M. Mandeville, Court of Appeals decision regarding Trustees of exempt Firemen's Benevolent Fund of NYC V. APM Roome, printed copy of laws of N.Y. regarding retirement of city employees, 1880-1923 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Rockaway Beach Volunteer Firemen's Benevolent and Protective Association, certificate of incorporation and membership roll, apparatus book, Atlantic Engine Co., By-Laws and programme, 1889-1901 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Assorted newspaper clippings of King's County Volunteer Firemen's Associations, 1904-1942 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Firemen's Association of State of New York, correspondence, 1915-1925 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - NYSCOAF: correspondence, primarily Brooklyn Council No. 16, 1893 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - NYSCOAF: correspondence, primarily Brooklyn Council No. 16, 1894 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - NYSCOAF: correspondence, primarily Brooklyn Council No. 16, 1895 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - NYSCOAF: correspondence, primarily Brooklyn Council No. 16, 1896 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - NYSCOAF: correspondence, primarily Brooklyn Council No. 16, 1897 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - NYSCOAF: correspondence, primarily Brooklyn Council No. 16, 1888 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - NYSCOAF: correspondence, primarily Brooklyn Council No. 16, 1899-1901 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - NYSCOAF: circular letters, meeting notices, 1893-1899 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - NYSCOAF: Brooklyn Council No. 16, reports to Board of Directors, 1893-1895 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - NYSCOAF: reports, 1896-1897 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - NYSCOAF: reports, 1898-1901 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - NYSCOAF: Brooklyn Council No. 16, resolutions and By-laws, 1894-1900 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - NYSCOAF: state organization installation ceremony and circular letters, 1893-1899 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - NYSCOAF: state organization, annual reports convention reports, treasurer's reports, 1889-1897 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Series 8: Photographs, 1880s-1920s; V1989.027; 4.5 Linear Feet in five boxes of various sizes (Box Framed Photographs 2, Box Prints by Accession OSX2, Box Framed Photographs 1, Box Prints by Accession, Box Prints by Accession OS12, Box Slides by Accession 3, Box 5, Item V1989.27.23, 26.1-23, 26.24, 27, 41, Flat file folder V1989.27.1-6, 48)
  The collection includes photographs relating to Brooklyn firefighting, primarily portraits of individuals and groups of firefighters, dating from the 1880s to the 1920s. The original accession includes some photographs that do not appear to have a direct relation to Brooklyn firefighting, such as a group portrait of the United Spanish American War Veterans (USWV) Camp No. 39 and an image of an industrial area of the Carroll Gardens/Gowanus neighborhood of Brooklyn.
- Series 9: Scrapbooks, 1829-1925
  The series contains scrapbooks relating to various Kings County fire departments, dating from 1829 to 1925.
  - Scrapbook, mainly New Lots (ledger 135), 1829-1887 (Box 67w)
  - Brooklyn Fire Items-Atlantic Hose Company No. 1 (scrapbook) (photocopy) (ledger 145), 1855-1869 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Twelve large membership certificates, broadside, and unbound scrapbook (photocopy), circa 1865-1900 (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook, Continental Engine Company No. 9 (photocopy) (ledger 123), 1863-1868 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - King's County Volunteer Firemen (scrapbook) (ledger 134), 1867-1925 (Box 68w)
  - Scrapbook (ledger 32), circa 1902 (Box 64w)
  - Scrapbook (ledger 50), circa 1913 (Box 65w)
  - Roll book, scrapbook of L. Hatfield (ledger 102), undated (Box 19)
- Series 10: Printed Material, 1844-1928
  The series contains printed matter for various King's County, New York, and out-of-state fire departments and associations (including annual reports, proceedings, manuals, and copies of the constitutions and by-laws) dating from 1856 to 1928. It also includes issues of the Fireman's Advocate and Knickerbocker Gazette (1844), The Fireman's Herald (1889, 1892, 1895), and The Firemen's Journal (1892-1893).
  - Annual Reports, Constitutions and By-Laws, Proceedings, Manuals, etc.: Kings Cty. Fire Departments and Associations, 1856-1916 (Box 11)
  - Annual Reports, Constitutions and By-Laws, Proceedings, Manuals, etc.: New York City and State Departments and Associations, 1865-1928 (Box 11)
  - Annual Reports, Constitutions and By-Laws, Proceedings, Manuals, etc.: Non-New York State Departments and Associations, 1887-1889 (Box 11)
  - Fireman's Advocate and Knickerbocker Gazette, Vol. I, Nos. 1, 2, 5, 6, 1844 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - The Fireman's Herald, 1889 (Box 222w)
  - The Fireman's Herald, 1892 (Box 223w)
  - The Fireman's Herald, 1895 (Box 224w)
  - The Firemen's Journal, 1892-1893 (Box 225w)
- Series 11: Artifacts and works on paper, circa 1850-circa 1905
  This series contains items from the collection that had previously been assigned to the BHS museum's collection of artifacts and works on paper. It includes the following:
  Helmet, circa 1850 (M1989.44.1)
  Horn, circa 1905 (M1989.44.36)
  Painted photograph of an unidentified volunteer firefighter, circa 1890s (M1989.44.117)
  Portrait drawing of a postman in uniform, circa 1890s (M1989.44.119)
  Color lithograph entitled "The First Fire Engine Ever Used in Brooklyn" (built by Jacob Boome, 1795). Printed by A. Brown & Co. for Henry McCloskey's Manual, 1863 (M1989.44.120)
- Series 12: Miscellaneous and unidentified, 1894-1946
  The series contains ledgers and other items relating to unidentified Kings County fire departments, as well as some miscellaneous material, dating from 1894 to 1926.
  - Firemen's Insurance Company, Minutes (ledger 35), 1894-1897 (Box 14)
  - Dues accounts (ledger 176), 1894-1895 (Box 24)
  - Building info, 1906-1916 (Box 186w)
  - Firebox locations and journal, 1898-1911 (Box 187w)
  - Repair log/reports, 1900-1920 (Box 188w)
  - Roll book (ledger 155), 1902-1907 (Box 23)
  - Receipts, accidents, etc., 1904-1905 (Box 189w)
  - Orders, 1906-1908 (Box 190w)
  - Inspection report log, 1910-1916 (Box 192w)
  - Office journal, 1917-1923 (Box 193w)
  - Combustibles record journal, 1938-1941 (Box 194w)
  - Combustibles record journal, 1942-1946 (Box 195w)
  - Fire prevention inspection record, 1938-1946 (Box 196w)
  - Journal, 1903 (Box 205w)
  - Journal, 1904 (Box 197w)
  - Journal, 1910-1911 (Box 198w)
  - Journal, 1912 (Box 199w)
  - Journal, 1912-1913 (Box 200w)
  - Journal, 1919 (Box 201w)
  - Journal, 1924 (Box 213w)
  - Journal, 1926 (Box 214w)
  - Journal, 1926 (Box 221w)
  - Address book (ledger 183), 1929 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous ephemera, circa 1938 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Dues accounts (ledger 17), undated (Box 66w)
  - Blank Building Inspection Journal, undated (Box 207w)
  - Fire Roll Journal, 1909 (Box 208w)
  - Blank Hook and Ladder Company Fire Record Book, undated (Box 209w)
  - Fire Roll, undated (Box 210w)
  - Blank ledger (Box 220w)